In today's video, I'm going to cover
absolutely everything that you need to
know about e-commerce operations.
I really wish I had this video when I
was creating The Oodie. We did over $650
million in sales, and it has been the
most challenging part of my business.
Marketing it's always been my specialty,
but operations simply because generally
how e-commerce brands are created, the
founder is very creative, they like
product, they can understand how to
arbitrage traffic. And then they
completely neglect the other side of the
business. So, they're generally right
brain orientated, creative orientated,
but they're not process orientated. But,
it's just such a negative thing, and you
really do need to understand kind of
everything in this video if you want to
achieve great things. So, we're going to
cover things like planning, we're going
to cover things about product, supply
chain management, freight, you name it.
For those that don't know me, I'm Davie,
I'm the founder of The Oodie. I also run
Daily Mentor, and in that I have over
figure brands doing over a million
dollars.
And they all struggle with this side of
the business as well. So, that's why I'm
creating this video. I just wish I had
it, and it's going to help a lot of
people. So, it's definitely more of a
specialized, more of an of an advanced
video,
uh but I think it's going to really
really help you out. Now, I'm going to
talk a lot about resources, like
spreadsheets, and a lot about 3PL
management, these kind of things.
Everything that I talk about today, I'm
going to use the whiteboard, but
everything I talk about is in the free
Shopify e-commerce course. So, I'm going
to start building some templates out for
you. I've also started working with
about 10 3PLs that I trust, and we've
started to get great rates from them,
and I think that the 3PL side of the
business, which is the third party
logistics, where a warehouse will
actually ship your goods for you,
is probably one of the most difficult
things to get right for brands, and you
really need someone that you can trust.
So, I've compiled a full list, and if
you just head to the description,
I'll give you instructions how to get
that list, and we'll introduce you and
make sure that that's right. So, they
are affiliates as well, uh but at the
same time it we're working very very
closely with you, and they will look
after you. So, to make you understand
just how important this side of the
business is, we were forecasting to do
something like 45 50 million dollars uh
in just like October November months,
and we had a provider for our on the
logistics side of the business that
completely couldn't ship any orders. We
had to turn off all promotions, and then
customers were getting the wrong
products, they weren't getting shipped
at all, and realistically we had no way
to actually fix the issue because we had
contracted this provider, and they were
just completely letting us down on the
other side of the world. In short, we
lost over 20 million dollars in lost
revenue, in my opinion, and that The BBC
ended a story on us saying that I was a
scammer, which is absolutely
heartbreaking for me cuz the customers
that we have are just so so important.
And it made me really want to do this
video is simply because I don't want you
guys to have to go through that. I don't
want you to have
I don't want you run out of stock. I
don't want you to have a 3PL that can't
ship orders. I don't want you to have
uh freight logistics companies when
you're shipping stuff on the water
completely mess up all of your timelines
and get you lots of negative reviews
simply because they've made the wrong
mistake. So, that's all the stuff that
we're going to cover today.
Um so, I think that
let's talk about what operations
actually are. In
to put it really simply, because you
actually have not only operations in the
general term, but you also have
marketing operations, you can have
finance operations. It's such a broad
term, and it pretty much encompasses all
of business. I will talk about the the
subsection of operations that we're
going to talk about today in a just a
bit. But in short, operations we have
the And by the way, don't judge the
handwriting. I was very reluctant to
actually use a whiteboard, I was going
to use the iPad, but anyway, we have
inputs,
and then we have processes,
and then we have the outputs.
Now,
this is pretty much most of business.
The aim of operations is to maximize the
outputs. One of the key things is always
just referencing the outputs, how the
customer experiences it, because a lot
of people will measure outputs and it
won't actually affect the customer. But
realistically, we're just trying to
maximize the output for the customer,
and we're trying to decrease the amount
of processes that we actually need
through efficiency, and we're trying to
decrease the amount of inputs that we
need, because then we are basically
getting more
for less. Processes, you're trying to
use automation to kind of decrease the
amount of load that it takes within
those processes, and then you're also
just trying to decrease the amount of
inputs that are actually going in,
because that's going to decrease your
cost as well. That's basically
operations as a whole, and every single
thing that we talk about today, you
know, when it comes to forecasting, how
can we do more for less, these kind of
things. So, just remember this formula.
So, what are
the fundamental departments that we'll
be talking about today. Hey, that wiped
off pretty good. So, we're going to
cover
uh starting at the front, we're going to
talk about product.
Now, I could do a 2-hour video on
product. It is such a large
uh piece of the puzzle, but I'm just
going to cover it probably more from an
operational standpoint. Then we're going
to talk about supply chain.
So, this is like more like getting the
product to your uh warehouse, because
then we have fulfillment.
And within supply chain, I'm probably
going to talk about forecasting or
planning. Some people will kind of put
that in their own subsection
uh as well. It's kind of neither here
nor there. And then we've probably got
as well
didn't really think about that. We've
also got customer service, which I'll
touch on briefly because I think it's a
important point of operations. So, we're
going to cover each of these things.
Obviously, you order the product, uh you
create the product, sorry. You then
order the product, you forecast the
product, you fulfill it to the customer,
and then the customer gets customer
service. This is a very expensive
process. There is a lot of people that
are required, and it will scale up the
amount of the amount of people that you
actually need for this process will
scale up as the business grows. One
thing to note, if you are just kind of
getting started with org charts, you're
generally going to have the CEO or the
founder up here, and then you're going
to have, you know, the CFO over here.
Then you're going to have a CMO, so
CFO or chief executive officer for CEO,
chief financial officer for the finance
side of things, chief marketing officer
for the marketing side, and then you're
going to have a COO, so chief operating
officer. And these are all of these
departments here
are going to be underneath this role
generally in most companies. Sometimes
product might be split up, sometimes
customer service might be split up, but
generally this is what I would
recommend.
Now, a big part of today's video that I
wanted to cover is how can I convince
these people how important this video
actually is, because all of my YouTubes
that get good views uh going to be me
talking about Facebook ads, me talking
about ways to arbitrage traffic, all the
sexy stuff that drives revenue. And I
think that there should be at least
one-to-one videos for this side of
things, but because it doesn't get many
views on YouTube, nobody does it. I'm
trying to change that for us here, but
realistically, if you think about
if you think about your business as like
a garden, let's say. When you plant
seeds to become plants and to harvest
them, that is going to be like product,
or even like marketing activities. Now,
I like to think of operations as
weeding. Eventually, if you don't if you
don't weed on a consistent basis on a
consistent cadence, you're going to get
so overgrown that all of the product all
of the all of the other seeds that
you're planting uh not going to grow, or
you're not going to get as many crops
from them. So, you really just need to
focus on that. I think the the main
issues for The Oodie
I would say came from planning.
So,
I think it was the second year of our
business, we were doing about 25 million
dollars revenue. This was pre-COVID
time, so pretty amazing business growing
already. I was like, yep, this is going
to be a really good thing. Then what
happened was COVID hit. I remember
sitting on my couch, and we just
launched YouTube ads just before it, and
I was like, wow, these YouTube ads are
really working. We're we're we're
growing so rapidly, my sales are up, you
know, I've done $200,000 today. And then
I remember just every single like day
after that for about 5 days, I didn't
even understand that I needed to order a
ton more product because COVID had
actually hit, and that was having a huge
impact on e-commerce. A lot of people
might not remember, but a lot of people
were just saying businesses as a whole
are going to die because of this.
There was obviously indications that
e-commerce was going to grow, but I
think that is like a fundamental
huge miss that the planning side of the
business we were just like, spend more
money, spend more money, spend more
money. And there was nobody within our
organization that was incredibly good at
operations and planning on a regular
cadence to go, "Okay, we need to order
way more stock for this and redo our
forecast." And in hindsight, if we had
that operational role within our
business, it could be probably 30-40%
bigger because we would have actually
executed really well during that period,
but instead we would just sold out
entirely. Now, I mentioned you know,
people that I've hired or certain roles
within the business, the org chart,
whatnot.
Am I saying that you need to go hire all
of these roles? Absolutely not. I
recognize that a lot of people watching
this video maybe just a be a single
founder. You know, you're starting to
get a little bit of traction or you're
just kind of generally curious about the
space.
When I drew this org chart down here,
you will be
pretty much in every single one of those
roles for a very long time, at least
until you're doing over a million
dollars. You you might contract to
freelancers and for a couple of things,
but you need to be an expert in customer
service, product, all of these kind of
things. So, whenever I talk about all of
these tasks and things that we need to
do
to optimize the business today,
you have two options. You can learn it
yourself, which is why I'm teaching it,
or you can hire someone for it. And
eventually, as your business gets to a
certain point, you will hire specialized
people for each of these roles, but in
the meantime, you actually need to just
use generalists. The other reason
operations is so important is because in
e-commerce, you have very few moats.
Anyone that follows along with Warren
Buffett, he loves to talk about moats.
And one of his favorite moats, aside
from technological, you know, network
effects, is brand itself. Now, we are in
e-commerce on a race to build a brand
because then we have some level of
protection. But there's actually kind of
like I would like to call it a soft moat
rather than a hard moat that you can
actually implement within your business
to stop all of these drop shippers
taking market share. And that is systems
and operations because
if you think about it, let's take Amazon
versus eBay as a really, really good
example.
There's a book, I think it's called The
Greatest Business on Earth. And there
was a period where people were looking
at eBay and saying that they
are the best business ever. Huge
margins, they don't need to touch any
product. They basically get a cut of
every single sale that's done in their
business. And operationally, they don't
have to touch anything. They're pretty
much just a software company. At the
same time, people were roasting Amazon.
They were saying, "What a terrible
business. They've never made money. They
look at their margins. They're investing
so much opex and capex into all of these
sides of the business, such as
warehousing."
Now, look how it's flipped.
And this is because Amazon invested
heavily into remember the equation, the
outputs for the customer,
and they created systems and processes
that now nobody can kind of really catch
up with.
Uh including even couriers themselves.
They're going to be the largest courier
network if not if they aren't already.
So, I think
not
thinking about a lot of this stuff that
we talked today as a huge asset to your
business. And the way that I look at
this is let's say we've got brand A.
This is the hoodie.
And we've got brand B.
Actually, it says B. These numbers are
not the hoodie. And then we've basically
got uh
and then we've got all of the costs of
the the side of the business that I was
talking about before. We've got freight.
We've got product cost.
We've got courier cost.
And we've got let's say warehousing.
There's going to be more variable costs
um that I'll talk about here.
Let's say brand A, their freight costs
$5.
Um
then let's say brand B, their freight
costs $6. Now, how is this going to
happen? So,
the freight side of the business, if
you're talking to lots of freight
providers, which I'm going to show you
exactly how to do, you're going to get
better rates, you can pick pick them off
against each other, that kind of thing.
And then let's say we've got the
cost of the product, $10,
$12.
So, realistically,
you can achieve a 20% incre- in better
price simply because you're negotiating
with your suppliers, you're comparing
multiple factories, maybe you're
de-speccing your product or something
like that. Then we've got the courier
side of the business,
$5
and then $8. How could this happen?
You're working with a better 3PL with
better rates, very, very plausible. And
you spent time actually negotiating with
these these couriers or even changing
the actual one that you're using, the
actual track that you're using. And then
let's say warehousing, it's a very small
cost. Let's just say $1 and $2 because
you've negotiated a better 3PL.
So, this product is now going to be $21
to get to the customer. This product is
going to be $28 to get to the customer.
This brand now has a whole another $7
that it can spend on marketing, which is
a lot. Let's say even like we've got a
$50 CAC.
We've got That is not a five. Sorry
about that. There, if you've got a $50
CAC, you know, they're going to be
making 14% more profit.
They could spend that on
team. They could spend that on so many
other things simply because they have to
spend time
optimizing the inputs of their
operations.
So, one thing I should say, this formula
that I just covered there, we're going
to cover it in detail in just a little
bit cuz I'm going to explain what
customer acquisition cost is, those kind
of things. I I don't want to keep it too
basic today. I want to make sure that
this is very valuable for brands that
are actually scaling as well.
But let's get into our first kind of
actual subsection of what we're talking
about today, actually
actual department, and we will go
through everything that we can do to
optimize that operational department um
and streamline the business. So, the
first department we're going to talk
about today is product. Now, product is
a such a large topic as I said before.
And depending on the type of store that
you have, let's say you're a clothing
store and you're launching multiple SKUs
in terms of different sizes and
different colors
versus a one-product store where you've
just created a product and it's starting
to scale.
Wildly different the amount of work that
it's going to take to manage suppliers,
manage the product development. But in
large part, the main place that I see
people make mistakes here
is
the first thing is tech packs.
A tech pack is short for technical pack.
And it encompasses every single detail
of your product. Now, the typical
process that you've probably have seen
even on my videos is you go onto
Alibaba, AliExpress, or you know, if
you're more advanced, you'll go to a
trade show and get the supplier details.
And you'll say, "Hey, I want this
product." And they'll give you the price
and they'll send you a sample.
That is
really risky
because there's so much ambiguity about
what that product is like on the
AliExpress listing or Amazon listing
compared to what you're actually going
to get delivered. So, for example, when
I first started calming blankets, I
think we did $10 million in its first
year, did about a million dollars
profit. So, it was growing very quickly.
The It was largely based on the trend.
It was just a really, really hot then.
Um so, our customer list was growing
very, very quickly.
I would go onto Alibaba and I would say,
"Hey, I want a thousand weighted
blankets just in gray." And then the
container would rock up after shipping
for 20 days on the ocean and
3 weeks manufacturing, even longer.
And we would open it up and we would
open a box and be like, "Wow, this is
beautiful." And then we would open
another box and it was a whole another
gray. And then we would open another box
and it was a whole another gray. And
then none of them would weigh the same
either. For a weighted blanket, that is
extremely problematic. And the the issue
isn't is the product okay because often
the supplier is saying, "Yeah, this is
it's still a great product." Which
probably it is, but the issue is when
you're selling a product based on how it
looks and feels and people are buying
two of the same product and they're
arriving and they're completely
different. And this is what a tech pack
solves. A tech pack is a document, which
I'll I'll put a link to an example tech
pack. And I'll also just put one up up
on the screen here so you can kind of
visualize it. But it covers every single
every single part of the product. So, a
tech pack includes one, a complete
drawing.
So, the complete drawing is going to be
so that people know exactly kind of what
the product looks like. And for
clothing, this is really, really
important because if you've got a hoodie
with a print on the front and then they
don't look at that drawing
because they don't scroll down to the
bottom to where it explains that there's
a print, the the drawing just clears
everything up. So, the complete drawing,
pretty obvious what it is. You just want
to make sure it looks pretty accurate.
It's got the right prints on it, the
right kind of size, the shape, the right
colors, approximately, but it's not
going to be the be-all and end-all
because it's the similar situation to
just like a product photo. It's not
specific enough. Then we're going to
have the fabrics. Now, you're going to
have things like the GSM, which is
basically the thickness of the product,
which is the density, the softness,
these kind of things. And realistically,
in the process of creating the product,
you're going to want if if it is there
is fabric components, you're going to
want to get strike-offs. So, these are
if there's a print on the product,
they're going to print on the right
fabric and they're going to send it to
you
or they're just going to send you a big
kind of photo with all of their
different fabric types.
And you can kind of select one from
there. Now, you're going to want to keep
this fabric and put it into the tech
pack in terms of the details of it. You
want to want to keep one on your side,
but GSM really clears things up because
I'll give you an example. We We're
getting complaints that our hoodies were
too thin and like what's what's going on
here?
And all we had to do, because we had a
tech pack at the time, is we cut out the
designated amount of size of the fabric,
we weighed it of these products and we
could show that our supplier was
actually undercutting and using the
wrong fabrics for it. We could get rid
of those products out of the market and
we could and the supplier replaced them
all. Without the tech pack, it's going
to be very hard to prove how, you know,
if they are undercutting on the fabric
side of things. The other thing is
you're going to want to put specifics
about how to treat the fabric. So, like
if you want to like an acid wash or
something like that, you can probably
put that within the fabric section. The
third one, now I think this is most
important for fabric for
clothing brands as well, is you're going
to want measurements.
And we're going to talk about this
a little bit more, but measurements
will,
especially for things like t-shirts, if
you don't have the proper measurements
on the sleeve, on how it fits on the
front versus the back, the product is
going to fit completely differently and
you're going to get a lot of complaints.
And even when you're switching
suppliers, these tech packs are going to
be essential for you to send them to a
second supplier so that you can get a
quick quote and actually, yeah, actually
transition suppliers easily. So, it's
well worth the investment. And then
fourth, we've got graphics.
Fifth, we've got like the hardware, you
know, zips, all of these kind of things,
different pockets. You just want to kind
of zoom in on those. There's so many
different ways to do your tech packs and
lots of people will give you different
ways. Realistically, if you have most of
these things, you're going to get rid of
probably 90% of your actual supplier
errors and you probably also want to
just add some reference.
So, just a reference pictures of all of
the samples that you have as well. It
will keep it organized. Now, I know I'm
recommending you to create these tech
packs, but it is quite a specialized
skill and it needs to be very, very
accurate. So, if you're struggling with
this or you don't currently have one for
your product, you can just go on to
Upwork
and you can send the product to the
Upwork person. You can write in a
fashion designer or a tech pack creator.
You can really write in anything based
on your product and they will be able to
manufacture one for you. And I think
that that's a really good freelancer to
have. It shouldn't cost you more than
200 bucks, but it'll be a really good
asset. Now, this is generally for
textiles, but all products are going to
have some form of tech pack. It's just
going to get way more complicated when
you're looking at more like hardware,
things that are injection molded, all of
that kind of stuff, but everyone should
have a tech pack. One other thing that
tech packs will allow you to do, which I
see a lot of people struggle with, is
grading. So, grading is taking sizes
from small, medium to extra large, those
kind of things. So, having these
measurements here and working with
someone that understands grading will
just give you a really, really good
product and avoid crazy mishaps where
your extra large just doesn't work. And
one final thing, sorry I forgot, is
you're going to want your labels as
well. So, making sure that you have your
company name, all of that kind of stuff
because some regions, if you don't even
have your company name on the product
itself or it's in the wrong position,
the swing tag/label,
you can actually get huge fines as well.
So, that will make sure that your
supplier does it right. This also
includes things like packaging as well.
Be very, very clear for the supplier if
you've got unique packaging. So, once
you've created this tech pack, the next
part is how to manage the suppliers and
how to get the product. Realistically,
as I said before, you've got a few ways
to create the product. Typically,
first-time founders, they will
actually outreach to their supplier to
create the product with the supplier.
This is good because it's very
cost-effective. It's very bad simply
because there's nothing unique about
your product and anyone can launch the
product. Also, your supplier actually
owns that IP unless you can get
something like exclusivity, which is a
relatively hard to do unless you're
doing huge volumes. This is why I often
recommend that if you have a little bit
of experience already in the field in
acquiring customers, you should be
actually working with a product
designer, fashion designer, a product
agency that specializes in physical
products to create this product in the
early stage and then work with the
either the supplier or these localized
manufacturers
to create the product, create the tech
pack and then go out to multiple
suppliers to kind of get pricing. Now,
one of the main mistakes that I see
people make managing with their
suppliers from an operational standpoint
is they use a lot of different forms of
communication.
And this is one of the strongest things
that Alibaba has ever done is something
called trade assurance. So, typically,
it was very back in the day, it was a
very hard to even transfer money to
China and it was very, very easy to get
scammed as well.
What I really recommend people to do to
make sure that their supply chain is
very, very dialed in and there's not too
many mistakes is always using the trade
assurance option within Alibaba.
If you
communicate all through Alibaba, through
the messages there and you have a tech
pack, when a product arrives and it is
incorrect, you can easily prove that
they have provided the wrong product
based on previous communications and the
tech packs and POs, which we'll talk
about in a sec, and you can get your
money back. But this is this kind of
brings me to
the other side of the supply management,
which is the legality side. We talked
about a little bit about them owning the
IP. That's probably about it, sometimes
unavoidable, but realistically, you want
to kind of come to terms with the
supplier around things like refunds.
What happens if the the product rocks up
and it's not the same or how much
tolerance do you have for them shipping
incorrect quantities? What happens if
they claim they've shipped the right
quantities but haven't? So, I'll add a
list of all of these things to consider
with your supplier as well.
These are the conversations that need to
happen prior to you actually sending
them 50, you know, 20 grand
because it's really, really important.
One option that you have with that side
of things is to get a contract in place.
Now, typically, I like legally,
everybody is always going to recommend
that you get a contract and I do
recommend it as well, but I have
operated without contracts before
and the truth is a lot, especially when
you're first getting started, the the
suppliers within China are not going to
want to deal with contracts at all. But
eventually, when you get to a point,
you're going to want a contract that's
signed and agreed from
from both parties about all of those
things that I just mentioned. This
contract is especially important if you
have a very unique product because you
need to protect your IP.
You can't just send a product over to
China because as soon as it works,
they'll just sell they'll give it to
other factories and multiple people will
be creating your product. So, if it's a
completely unique product, get the
contract. If not, you might need to
operate and build some good faith and
build some relationship with the person
before you can even negotiate a
contract. Realistically, when you're
talking to your supplier,
and let's let's say you've got the tech
pack for the person
or you kind of know
that you want to create that product
with that supplier, you've got a few
main points
that you want to discuss with the
supplier on the on the product side,
which is going to be imperative to the
rest of the operational process, which
is the first is MOQs, which is your
minimum order quantities. Really
important cuz you can't order 20
products of a custom product. That's not
going to happen. You're going to have to
order a lot.
Two, you're going to want to understand
the price.
And then three,
you're going to want to understand lead
times. Now, this is the time that it
takes to actually manufacture the
product, not the time to ship the
product cuz that's within the supplier's
control. Typically, we might want to
work with a supplier that has a higher
price, but they have lower MOQs because
you don't have the budget to do it. Or
maybe you really want to work with
someone with, you know, hoodie can
sometimes do this. We'll pay for the
higher price for the product, but simply
because they have lower lead times,
which allows us to manage cash flow
better. I think we really we just want
to highlight this side of things because
I see a lot of people, they create the
product and they're like, let's go.
Let's I'll order it in. They don't
consider the unit economics of their
business. And this first negotiation
stage of the product, even if you're a a
relatively experienced business with
like five, 10 people, is often even like
I've seen businesses with 50 people
where this price negotiation just
doesn't get considered within the rest
of the business. So, if I created an
hoodie that was just so specked out, it
had, you know, inflatable arms to swim
in or something stupid like that or it
had electronics in it, let's say it had
speakers in its its hood. Chances are,
you know, that would sell. It would
definitely sell at $20, $30, but the
truth is the price of that product is
going to be more like
$50, $60. So, therefore, I would have to
sell it for $200. It immediately rules
out that product from being viable. So,
this price negotiation stage is
important for if you've got multiple
stakeholders with a business to be
considered about what you can sell it
for.
Now, one operational tip that I have at
this stage of the business, let's say
let's say you've placed the order. I'm
going to give you a few more supplier
tips.
But, a really really great operational
thing that you can do at this point is
put the unit economics within both your
purchase orders, but also out on the
Shopify side. While we're talking about
price, I think this is a really
important part where I see most people
go wrong on their operations and finance
side of their business is they don't
actually understand their unit economics
and they do not track profit on a daily
basis. Tracking profit on a daily basis
is fundamental to your e-commerce
business. And if you don't understand
the true price of your product, even
like and you can start calculating it at
this stage, then you you there's a good
chance that you're going to spend and
you're going to forget that you have tax
on the product, sales tax, and then
you're going to have to spend all of
your profits eventually and fix your
books. It's just a nightmare. So, how do
we make sure at this stage that we have
that that we have a viable product and
how do we optimize the rest of the
process that I talked about today to
make sure that
you know, we're we're not actually
losing money on orders. So, your unit
economics of your product is going to be
you've got your cost of product. So,
this is just how it how much it cost to
manufacture. Then, you've got the
freight.
Now, we've talked about this before.
Then, we've got the courier.
Then, we've got storage.
Then, we've got duties.
Now, duties are very different from
sales taxes and you need to understand
the actual
uh cost of the duties for the region
that you're importing into. For example,
importing from China to the US,
depending on the product, will have
different duties for for that side of
things. And that is we're not going to
get that money back. It's not like sales
tax where if we charge $10 to the
customer and then we spend $5, we get
the different we have to pay the
difference in in that region for sales
tax. It's just not like that. It's it's
basically a sunk cost. Um when you'll
you'll see that I don't actually have
uh the the sales tax within this
calculation because I'm actually
removing it from the calculation. We're
calculating all of this this side of the
business at this stage
uh excluding all of the sales taxes.
Now, what that will allow you to do is
you'll get this uh you'll get this
number and you can
one, put it in your purchase orders, but
two, you can put it into the back end of
Shopify, which will allow you to create
daily profit reports that include all of
these side of side of the business.
Then, what happens with most reporting
tools? So, Triple Whale, I leave an
affiliate link and an offer in the
description uh for you guys to look at
that. But, realistically, because we
understand the true cost of the product,
then
basically, all of these other apps
include marketing. So, these
which is a variable cost on a daily
basis because this will change based on
how much you spend. And then, as also as
well, you've got I guess payment fees,
which is again going to be probably
considered within all of these automated
tools or you can just build a simple
spreadsheet to to track this. So, while
we're on this price thing, I think I
probably should have explained it a
little bit
uh earlier, but
I think probably one of the main
operational and financial mistakes that
I see e-commerce break
e-commerce brands make is that they are
not tracking daily profit. Daily profit
needs to include a lot of metrics and it
starts at the supplier level. All right?
Like cuz we're we're getting the
supplier
uh costings. But, let me just show you
exactly how to calculate this and how to
track it on a daily basis because
everyone needs to be doing So, to
calculate our profit per product sold,
we have the
uh sale price of the product
minus the cost of the product.
And that is what we're talking about
before, that supplier cost that you've
now got from them. Then, we're minus in
the freight as well.
Um which I'm going to talk about how to
calculate the freight uh costs. But,
basically, we have one big large
container, we're putting 1,000 products
into it, and it's costing us $1,000,
then it's going to be $1 per unit there
as well. So, it was generally smaller
cost unless you're shipping something
like furniture if you're using sea
freight. Where freight can add up a lot
is obviously if you're using air
freight, uh which is much much quicker,
but can be quite expensive.
Then, we've got the courier cost to the
customer, which is you you've got you've
basically got all of your 3PL costs
here, but we can separate it out to more
so pick pack
as well.
So, this is just getting a little bit
more granular
as well. And then, you've got storage,
which you can also calculate, but it's
quite a minuscule cost as well.
Now, the other big metric that you have
here
is you've got two other things. So, I'm
going to put them on a different line
and explain why. So, you got minus your
marketing,
which is your customer acquisition cost,
uh which you'll see in Facebook or I'll
I'll explain that a little bit more. And
then, you've got your payment fees.
Now, you can see these are all the
operational costs that we've been
talking about today that we're trying to
optimize.
These are what we refer to as Oh, sorry.
And then, we've got one other thing,
which is our duties
as well.
So, these
are all the operational costs. These are
what we call variable costs. By the time
the product arrives at your warehouse,
you should have no question about every
single one of these metrics. These, even
this one, you can kind of approximate.
Marketing is going to be uh you're going
to have to make some assumptions there.
And generally, we want to make sure that
we calculate the all of these side this
side of the business.
And what we're going to do is we're
going to put that into the back end of
Shopify where it says cost per product
in in Shopify.
What this will allow you to do is use
all of the reporting within Shopify or
you can use something like Triple Whale.
I'll leave the link for the description
in the description for them. Uh I highly
recommend those guys. They it's does all
of this and automates the reports. Or
you can build some free custom reports
as well using Looker um and integrating
there. Or you can just use a simple
Excel spreadsheet where you're inputting
all of these costs on a daily basis, the
variable costs on a daily basis to
calculate your net profit. But,
realistically, the way the reason why I
recommend putting all of these costs
into Shopify is because, yeah, we can
just integrate it so simply with a tool
like Triple Whale and they then
integrate with the marketing channels
for us. On a daily basis, we'll say,
"How much have you spent on marketing?"
It probably pick up all the payment fees
as well. And then, it will tell you
exactly it will just assume all of these
costs are consistent and it'll give you
your daily profit.
Where I see people go wrong with this is
one, they fail to calculate these costs,
the freight courier cost, and the 3PL
costs. And then, they also stuff up the
tax side of things. So, duties is a sunk
cost. Duties isn't the same as sales
taxes. If you're importing over a
certain threshold into a certain region,
such as China to
China to the
to the United States, they're going to
be duties depending on the product
category, of course. Whereas, Australia
China to Australia, there's the free
trade agreement, so you're not going to
pay duties there. So, you need to
understand those costs. The other thing
that I see people make is they fail to
incorporate sales taxes somewhere.
So, I'm assuming all of this stuff is
excluding sales taxes, okay?
The other place I see people go wrong is
the sale price. You need to make sure
that in the back end of Shopify when
you're setting this up, that you're
considering and you have the checkbox
that the
uh sales taxes will be charged to the
customer. Then, you just need to make
sure that that's feeding through to any
other reporting. So, you basically are
including uh GST or sales taxes in all
of these equation or not including it.
Just make sure that you've considered
that within this, so you're actually
getting a proper uh profit over here.
So, back to the product development
process. I'm going to explain one of the
most critical tools that you can use,
which is called a critical path. Uh I
mean, critical I'm critical. But,
realistically, this is something that
you need to get familiar with because
it's the best way to align teams, but
it's also the best way to ensure that
you are efficiently
doing everything as well as possible.
You're bringing products to market,
you're handling the development process
uh as as efficiently as possible. Before
I explain what a critical path is,
I think it's worth noting that
in the fashion
process or any product development
process, you're going to have
as I said before, you're going to have
to get a strike off the prints. Then,
you're going to get a first sample.
Then, you might get a finalized
production sample. There are so many
stages of this side of things. And then,
you'll get what's called a QC. Now, QC
is where a quality control agency will
actually go to the factory. They'll use
your tech pack again as a reference and
they'll weigh the product, they'll
measure the product, they'll do all
kinds of things, they'll check the
Pantone color.
And I highly, highly recommend that
every single first time that you use a
manufacturer, even the second and third
time, that you're using a QC agent to go
check the product. Now again, one of the
best things about Alibaba is they have
an inbuilt QC function where you can
just say, "Hey, send a QC agent out to
this order." Or you can use any of the
other ones like SGS. It's quite
expensive and big, but they do
compliance as well. So, I highly
recommend first time you're using it,
get a QC agent. But, you can see all of
these steps of the process and if you
failed to get the sample on time, you
might fail to get the product on time,
you might miss Christmas trade period,
and then you'll get stuck with all of
the product come January, February. The
way that we solve this is the critical
path. So, in short, a critical path
the main things
that we need to know
is first, we define every single step
of the process.
And you can do this with your team
member or you can just write it out.
The second step is we're going to
sequence all of these events in the
correct order.
Now, you can use a project management
tool like Asana, I use monday.com.
Really impartial about which one you
use, they're all pretty much the same.
You can use Notion. But, you really want
uh some people use Excel as well. You
just want all of these things visible,
all of every single task, and in the
right order, and then you're going to
define the time it takes to do them.
So, for example, getting a sample sample
being shipped from China might take 5
days from DHL. Every single granular
part of the process needs to be defined
within this critical path. Then what we
can do is we assign dates to them.
So, let's say we're going to do a hoodie
launch for this product.
We bring up our critical path and again,
you don't need to make this template
every single time, but you can generally
understand what the critical path is,
and we
might change a few things like the the
time that it's going to take for this
product because it's going to take a
little bit longer, but we can then,
because we know how long everything's
going to take, we can set dates to every
single uh step of the process. And this
is why I sometimes project management
tools are really good. We can set
reminders when something has gone
overdue on its estimated date. And what
then what that will do, it will either
push all of the future dates forward, or
there may be some overlapping
uh
overlapping times that create a little
bit of flex. Or uh it's referred to as
actual slap.
So then, all we need to do is monitor on
a daily basis.
And typically, these other project
management tools, a lot of people are
going to be able to edit these sheets
and change things. You can get your
suppliers to edit them as well if you
want. Typically, I don't recommend that
because the suppliers can manipulate
things and then you can't actually see
it. So, one person kind of monitoring
and owning this process each step of the
way is really important. So, I highly
recommend uh assigning roles as well.
The good thing about these project
management tools as well is you can
yeah, just set up notifications when
something blows out uh to notify the
person that is it responsible for it.
So, they'll get a notification, they can
change the rest of the process or just
notify the rest of the team. Now, if we
follow that critical path all the way to
the end of the process, we're probably
going to get Well, not all the way to
the end, but on the supplier side, we're
going to come to something that's called
place a PO, which is just place what's
called purchase order.
Before that stage, though, you're going
to have you're you're going to ask the
question, "How much product do I order?"
Now, typically, I see this as being
the most challenging part of a lot of
e-commerce businesses.
And this is because, you know, typically
in the industry, some of these big box
retailers and stuff like that, they will
have variants of their forecast of like
what they think they're going to order
what they think they're going to sell to
what they ordered of like 5%. But,
realistically, if you're selling out
consistently or you have huge
fluctuations, you're not going to get
anywhere close to that. We misforecast
by 50% even where we're, you know,
growing growing quite rapidly or have
some level of stability.
So, understanding how much product to
order is really important. When you're
first ordering the product, you're
generally going to be using other
products that are similar within the
space, or your best guess based on your
marketing activities just recently.
That being said, forecasting is just the
most essential part of the business
because if you get it wrong, let's say
you've got a successful business and
it's growing and growing and growing,
and you start expanding SKUs. So, you're
like, "I want a black blanket now, a
gray blanket, a blue blanket."
SKU expansion and ordering too much
stock,
all of your money, all of your profits
will go sit into inventory. And you will
no longer have any money to acquire new
customers or even pay your taxes. And
it's actually an existential risk to
your business.
So, getting this wrong on the low end
because they have no stock,
let's say, is going to give you $0
revenue, which can also send you out of
business if you've got lots of fixed
cost.
Getting this on the high end and
ordering way too much inventory will
also send you out of business. So,
realistically, we should be looking at
this on a weekly, fortnightly, or
monthly cadence, and I'm going to show
you exactly how to do it. All
forecasting is as we're trying to find
one of two things. Actually, we're
trying to find both, sorry. Is at what
date
do I reorder?
Which is basically a replenishment date.
And then two,
how much
do I order?
Seems pretty obvious, right? But, there
is a lot of variables that we need to
consider. And I'm going to have to speak
generally because, you know, something
like the Audi where we have a whole
dedicated team member looking at every
single SKU, every single product we've
sold the last 4 years of history, is
going to be very different to someone
just starting out in business. But,
speaking generally, I think there's a
few main things that we need to do.
The first is we can look at
uh certain tools that we can use. Now,
I use Excel and I've tested some very,
very expensive demand planning tools,
but because our team a lot of people
need a lot of flexibility within our
company, we just continue to use Excel.
If you went to something like
Woolworths, they're going to have a
software for this like a big
supermarket. Uh at the same time,
there's also inbuilt uh inventory
management tools in certain ERPs like uh
NetSuite, those kind of things. But, I
still we always seem to end up back at
Excel.
The problem with this is that if you
don't have a dedicated team member and
you're just a single founder and you're
trying to build out these forecasts
yourself, some people really struggle
with Excel formulas. And I I still
believe that there's a lot of
opportunity for uh a Shopify app to
solve this, especially with AI. I've
tested a few of them, but the one that I
keep coming back to and recommending is
Inventory Planner. I started using this
probably 2 years ago. I'll leave again
an affiliate link in the description. Uh
they're they're not paying me to say
this, it's just I just randomly signed
up to their affiliate knowing that I was
going to talk about them because I
really do think that they allow us to do
the the next steps that I'm I'm going to
talk about. Realistically, any of these
tools, all we're trying to do is get
visibility and clarity on previous
results so that we can make certain
assumptions about the future.
And
the best way that you can do that is the
first side of things where I see people
go wrong is they select the wrong dates.
So,
let me explain that.
The selecting a period, let's say
let's say you're
kind of out of stock for half a month
and then you're in stock for the rest of
the 15 days. I'll see people grab those
30 days and forecast out the next 90
days based on those numbers, not uh not
recognizing that they were extremely out
of stock in those those 15 days. So,
realistically, it would have been a much
more accurate way uh by grabbing the 15
days that they were in stock and
extrapolating that out because this is
really what forecasting is all about.
We're trying to compare
year on year
or month on month
sales and make certain assumptions about
the future.
So, if you've got less than a year of
business or you're even less than 2
years old and you've been growing
quickly,
realistically, you're going to be
looking at month on month. So,
let me just draw a little bit of an
example here. If we graph out our uh
sales for our product, let's say
January,
February, March. Oh, that's a B.
March, April,
May.
And then we look at this SKU over here.
Let's say SKU
one. Let's just say that's a black
hoodie or something like that.
And we say our sales for this product is
100 in January,
and a lot of the tools or you can custom
build this in Excel will show this.
Let's say we do 120,
like 145,
175. So, that's a about a 20% growth
rate.
If we looked at that and graph that out,
we would assume that it's going like
that. That's uh 20 about a 20% growth
rate.
We could assume that March is going to
be something more like that because it's
quite a linear slightly exponential
line.
This is the easiest scenario to
forecast. We're looking at
month-on-month revenue for that
particular SKU and making an assumption
about the future month. Where things get
really, really difficult is when there's
something called seasonality for our
product. And all e-commerce businesses
will 90 95% of e-commerce businesses are
going to have huge seasonality because
of Black Friday and these other
promotional events. So, if we come back
here, what is a very likely scenario or
forecast that we need to be able to
visibly see to predict is we got July,
August, September, October, November.
Always freaks me out that it says Jason.
We might have
you know, 205 and then we'll have 2,000
in October when Black Friday starts to
kick and then we might have 4,000 in
November. So, this is definitely not a
20% growth rate. This is more like this
this and then come December, it'll just
drop straight away or as soon as the
cut-off date, so we have a cut-off here
of Christmas ship shipping time, of
course.
So, realistically, we need to be able to
predict these periods because these
periods are eventually where you will
make
80% of your profits for the year. And if
you stuff this up, it's just game over
for you. And this brings me kind of to
my next thing that we need to be able to
do within these forecasting tools, which
is apply
a sales
growth rate.
And if you're using Inventory Planner,
it's really good because you can go into
the the revenue side of things and just
on a monthly basis say, "I'm going to
grow 20%, 30%, 40%." I'll leave a
template for this as well so you can do
it in Excel. Um but again, it is really
it can just break every now and then.
But, we're applying growth rate. Now,
how do we find seasonality because this
is the the main factor?
If we're a very new business, we can use
something like Google Trends and we can
write in beach tents and we can see
where it spikes because
the other main seasonal thing that's
going to happen aside from promotions or
holiday gifting
is going to be the nature of your
product. What is it's obviously when
it's winter, we sell a lot more wearable
blankets. Beach tents, we're going to
sell a lot more during summer. So, you
need to understand and you've got
northern hemisphere and southern
hemisphere is opposite polar opposite
with seasonality. So, you need to
understand that for say something like a
winter product, if we had July here, our
sales might come down and then come back
and then there might be a bit less of a
spike in this October, November. These
are the things that you just really need
to be thinking about. And this is why I
I highly recommend
when you start to get some traction,
let's say you're you're doing some
decent profits, you're paying yourself a
wage, hiring a someone that actually
understands and can spend time to look
at this thing on a weekly basis is just
it's just going to pay dividends. It
doesn't need to be a full-time uh
forecaster or demand planner or
merchandise planner. It can actually
just be an operations manager that one
is able to handle this and bring their
assumptions to you as a founder or you
just need to own it yourself. So, once
we've considered all of that and we've
applied our growth rate, one thing that
I remember what we're trying to find
out, we're trying to find how much we
need to order and when we need to order
it to manage cash flow as best as
possible. So, how do we what are some
other things that we need to consider
and put into both our tool or or our
spreadsheet so we can get this? The
first one is your lead times
which we talked about before from your
supplier.
If you put in this tool that it takes
100 days to get the product, it's going
to want you to order much quicker
because it's going to take a lot of time
to actually get the product. The other
thing you need to assume is the days of
stock.
This refers to how much stock you are
actually going to want to hold on to in
terms of your current sales velocity.
So, if you're selling 100 products
uh a month and 30 days in a month, then
you're selling about three products a
day. That is your daily sales velocity.
Your monthly sales velocity is 100
products. The days of stock simply says
that that's how many days of stock that
you have available to sell at the
forecast that you've kind of assumed.
Some tools are a little bit different
here. There there's going to be kind of
two metrics. First of all, it's like the
current days of stock. This is the how
much inventory you have. But then, when
you're actually using some of these
tools, you also need to put in how much
inventory you actually want. The typical
days of stock, it really depends on
industries and the age and and
variability of the business, the
volatility of the business, sorry, will
be 4 weeks, 8 weeks or even 12 weeks.
So, you want to consider how volatile
your business is but also how much money
you have to actually invest in the
inventory to calculate that number. And
then the third thing that some people
ask for or consider
most people do is safety stock as well.
This is just a a number that if you
made a mistake here with the days of
stock lead times or
uh sales really kind of picked up, you
have an element of buffer. You can
probably just put 5 to 10 days or
something like that for for this metric.
But realistically, if you're adding a
little bit of buffer on your lead time,
which you should be, should be taking
your average lead time uh in case things
are kind of going wrong there and you're
uh
giving yourself enough days of stock in
outlaying the right amount of capital
there, realistically, the safety stock
shouldn't shouldn't come into play. Then
once we've input all of that, we should
get a uh sales out in
when your product should sell out and
then also a replenishment amount.
Once you know that, you can go ahead and
place your first purchase order. Now,
the management of POs is one of the main
operational mistakes that I see
e-commerce founders make.
And it's because it's a it's a
relatively simple system. For those that
don't know, a purchase order is a
agreement between basically you and
supplier, somewhat of agreement. It's
basically just an invoice. You are
saying, "I want this product, this
price, these quantities. I want it
shipped here
and and a couple of other details as
well."
But, typically, lots of people either
aren't creating POs and they're just
creating orders on Alibaba and ordering
them.
Or they're not making sure that the PO
is utilized across the rest of the
company.
Because a PO is going to affect finance
because they're the ones paying the
invoices. It's going to
affect the operations side of the
business, so even the stock side of the
business because if
certain products are going to come in at
certain times, that's also going to
affect marketing as well because they're
going to want to push certain products
when they come in and want to understand
when they're going to come in. Then
you've also got customer service as
well. Imagine if you discontinued a
product or if you had a PO just about to
land but you're actually refunding
customers. Absolute disaster. So,
visibility and accessibility of these
POs and the management of them is
critical.
And there's multiple ways we can we can
skin this and I've seen some some really
good systems in place.
Side small side note, this is where an
ERP comes critical for brands doing over
30 over 50 million dollars. Because an
ERP is going to handle 90% of the things
that we talked about. There's two that I
recommend, not paid to say this at all,
NetSuite but it's very, very expensive
and I've heard good things about
forsale.io. A lot of people I respect
like Ridge Wallet, these guys are raving
about this ERP because they uh they they
can be so expensive. They're over 200
grand. We probably spent well over that,
you know, upwards of a half a million
dollars to get this in place.
But, the good news is there are some
cheaper solutions in the meantime when
you are just starting out to keep
organized in this area such as using
either your accounting software or using
Inventory Planner itself to manage the
POs.
Big issue with this is that we are going
to need a second place where all of the
roles that I just talked about, customer
service, marketing, they need to be able
to see the POs and POs can change a lot
as well. Often, a product will will get
an order at the 3PL and they'll be you
know, it'll be missing 500 500 units of
a certain SKU or less if you've got big
products.
And that creates complications. Also,
they might already tell you that they
you're missing that product and you'll
still ship the order anyway.
So, what I recommend is having two
systems. First, you've got the PO
system, which should be on your
accounting software, such as Xero or
MYOB or anything like that.
You're sending off those POs there, and
that will then match up to the deposits
that you're making to your supplier, and
also the the final payments to your
supplier.
But then you also have a second at a
Google Drive
or Airtable, a Google Sheet that all of
your team can access and see all of the
POs. And on that sheet, we're really
going to want to make sure that we have
multiple things.
To create the sheet, once the PO gets
placed, we're going to copy across the
what products
are there on a SKU level. We're also
going to copy up how many.
We're also going to have uh the PO
number as well.
Now, once you've got all of this stuff
in the sheet and you've created the PO,
we can then
do uh work with our freight logistics.
Now, this is a a bit of a tricky
situation for some people that don't
understand it. A freight provider is
basically a company, a logistics
company, that manages spots on a cargo
ship, on a uh container ship, and they
organize the container to be shipped
from your supplier to the warehouse that
you're talking about, like your 3PL or
even your home.
The best process for this is firstly,
you need to make sure that you talk to
probably someone locally in your area.
If you're in the States, work with a
freight provider in the States. And
you're going to want to get two to three
of these people at one given time,
because then you can compare their rates
and bring the efficiency up because
they're going to compete for your
business.
Once you have the right freight provider
and you've compared rates for that
month, you are then going to
yeah, let them know that they've sent
this PO. You can CC them in the
communication, or you can just connect
them with your supplier, and they'll
manage a lot of the process.
But they're going to come back to you
with a lot of details about how they're
shipping your products that you've paid
for to the next warehouse. They're going
to give you something like
the estimated
departure date.
They're also going to give you the
estimated arrival date, or just our ETA.
Then they're also going to give you uh
the
vessel number,
the bill of lading,
and a bunch more details. You really
want to put a lot of this information
within this kind of master spreadsheet,
this internal spreadsheet, so you can
see this departure date, this ETA. You
can communicate easily with the supplier
about the when the shipment is leaving,
and there's just so many important
things that will happen here. You're
also going to want to add the you're
constantly going to want to update this
estimated arrival time if the vessel
gets pushed back, and you can notify
people. You might want to put the actual
um arrival date
and and departure date as well, so you
can kind of track that
over time. If you're using air freight,
this is probably just going to be a
tracking number, um but you're still
going to want the estimated dates as
well. The main mistake that I see people
make here is and and just across this
whole video is not being organized. If
you are not putting a dedicated amount
of time to update these sheets and
you're like, "Oh, I'll do it a little
bit later." It's just not going to work,
because you're going to forget things.
People are going to make assumptions
based on the sheet that they have access
to that aren't actually true. So, this
is where a lot more resources comes in
handy when you're crossing over the 5,
10 million dollar mark. But at the same
time, just make sure that you're
religious about updating this based on
the information that your supplier is
giving you. I don't recommend allowing
suppliers to update this sheet at all.
It should be internal use only. And if a
supplier has changes, they should be
communicating through to you through
that one communication channel, probably
Alibaba, which your team can have access
to, and you can make comments and
changes on the sheet and notify people
in like Slack message. Okay. So, the
product is on its way to you now.
Where can we go wrong here? Let's chat
about 3PLs. I talked about what 3PLs are
at the start of the video. If you're
drop shipping, this isn't going to be
too relevant to you because drop
shippers, they'll ship directly from
their
factory uh to the the customer. But at
the same time, you should definitely
listen because I highly recommend
transitioning away from drop shipping,
providing that uh you're trying to build
a brand and have a great customer
service. I've talked about that a lot on
the channel.
When you're looking at looking for a
3PL, there's a few main things. If
you've already got a successful
business, what you're going to do is
you're going to do what's called an RFP,
which is called request for pricing.
In that RFP, you're going to give people
your forecasts, all the dimensions of
your product, your previous results.
Forecast is probably the main one
because we are generally a growing
business, and we're trying to get them
really excited about the future. We're
trying to get them to compete for the
business. And you'll create this master
document with all of these details, and
you'll go to multiple 3PLs. Again, I've
got some that I really recommend and I
trust
that you can uh access and email.
But
you want to go to multiple. Similar to
the freight forwarder, they're going to
compete for your business. You're also
going to want to go and visit the 3PL as
well. If you can't actually set foot in
there or at least uh see what their
facilities look like inside, that is a
huge huge red flag. We've gone to one uh
that was competing for the Audeez
business, and they were like, "Well, the
pricing is really good." They were
stealing Woolworths shopper Woolworths
shopping trolleys from the Woolworths
down the street to cart products from
one part of the warehouse to the other.
It's really not what we're looking for.
Although it's pretty pretty uh nifty and
cost-saving. So, it's similar to going
to your supplier's factory, if you can
do that. You're just going to get a
wealth of information. You're just
basically looking for a well-run
organization.
The information that we're looking to
get from our 3PL. Let me just talk about
3PL management generally. First of all,
I really want them to be wanting using
the barcodes because
if they're not scanning in barcodes,
both scanning in and scanning out,
there's going to be a huge question when
it comes to
"What happened to this product? Um why
am I missing this product at the end of
the month or at the after 2 years and
it's just suddenly gone?"
People are just going to point fingers.
So, barcodes is a an element of accuracy
and will generally be correlated with
accuracy. The other thing that we really
want is like an eagerness to work with
you.
I think that
it's not great being the smallest brand
at these 3PLs because they're just not
going to give you the best service.
Sometimes it's not being the best being
the biggest brand, either.
But at the same time, you do want to be
a valuable customer to them, and
generally just how their sales staff
treat you should be indicative of that.
The other thing is price.
This is a big component, obviously, of
3PLs and something that you I'm sure
you've considered. We have three forms
of price, I guess. We have uh pick pack,
which is the cost for someone to grab
the product from within their warehouse
and then ship it. Uh we considered that
in our unit economic formula before.
We've got inbounds, which is the cost it
takes for them to unload the container
or the air freight and put it into their
warehouse. Now, if you've got a very it
it depends on the business. This can be
material or not. You might want to
consider this in your unit economic
formula, but sometimes it is such a
small amount that it's probably not
necessary. And then we've got outbound
costs.
This is something you really need to
understand because outbound is going to
be a huge cost for your business. If
you're using something like Australia
Post or UPS if you're in the States,
Royal Mail if you're in the UK, the
outbound rates are going to be very
hugely.
And each 3PL will generally have their
own account with these couriers. This is
why you can get huge variance between
one 3PL versus the other because if
they've got Gymshark shipping out their
product, they might have incredible
rates that you can then piggyback on.
Whereas if they're a brand new 3PL, you
honestly might be able to get even
better rates than them. This is where
the shady practice around 3PLs can
sometimes come in. They will blend these
costs across the board and really create
like a fugazi around what they're
actually charging and where. But the
main thing that you need to remember is
just if you've got all of these variable
costs for your business, you can
understand and compare each 3PL in that
category, and more importantly, you can
actually audit the 3PLs at the end of
each month.
So,
this this isn't just like a I'll sign
the contract
and I'll forget about these costs, and
I'll just see it in my uh profit and
loss at the end of each month.
This is you need to create an Excel
spreadsheet that estimate how much of
each of these costs are based on the
sales that your Shopify store has done
for that period, so that you are not
getting overcharged on a monthly basis.
It's absolutely shocking to me of all of
the Daily Mentor clients,
I would say probably 30 to 40% of them
are getting overcharged in certain areas
simply because they are taking the word
for it of either the couriers or the
3PLs themselves. The other cost here
we'd have is storage as well, but I
think that that can be quite a minuscule
cost for you as well. Unless your
product is is quite large, like the Udi,
storage probably isn't going to be a
hugely material cost, but I definitely
would still check it and I would still
be auditing it. One thing to note about
the management of 3PLs, remember when I
was talking about the purchase order
just being integral to this entire
process,
you are going to receive that purchase
order
at the 3PL level, which will then update
your Shopify inventory. So, you want to
make sure that everything is accurate
along that process as well, because the
3PLs are going to want what's called an
ASN, an advanced shipping notice. I
think that's what it's called. So, you
want to send the
that that internal spreadsheet.
You can either create a summary of that
or the purchase order providing there's
enough details to say, "Hey guys, this
is coming." Because otherwise they're
just going to get blindsided by the
stock and it might take ages to unload
and you can get a bunch of extra costs
for like storing the container or not
unloading it in time. While we're still
setting up this 3PL,
it's really important that we get an
SLA, a service level agreement. This is
a contract that states all of these
things that we're talking about.
Obviously not uh eagerness, but it's
saying, "This is the level of service
that we'll provide." And within that
SLA, there's going to be certain things
like picked on time.
So, the 3PL itself will guarantee that
the products will be picked at a certain
time and shipped at a certain time. This
can be huge hugely problematic,
especially in promotional periods.
Because if you if they if they're saying
that they're going to pick it within
24-48 hours, and then it during Black
Friday, they have an amazingly important
client and they failed to forecast their
own staff members and then suddenly your
pick your pick time blows out to 7 days.
It takes them 7 days start picking
products. You can guarantee that your
actual outbound
your outbound times are going to take
ages as well, because all of the
couriers are backed up. Suddenly, this
is the main issue and it's why it
e-commerce brands can just get so many
negative reviews around the Christmas
period, because the time to pick and the
time to actually ship just really blows
out. And this is why our service level
agreement for when they will pick on
time needs to be explicit and I believe
that they all need some level of
negative consequences if they fail to
achieve on this pick. Maybe it's a
discount on that or maybe it's
completely free for that actual pick.
The other thing that we can track and we
do this manually at the moment is
delivered on time.
We track this from a customer service
metric as well. If we can see that
there's,
you know, under 95 under 95% of products
being delivered on time, we can then go
and investigate, is it because they're
taking too long to pick? Is it because
the courier is taking longer and we can
actually talk to them about discounts
and refunds? And we can dissect the
problem as well. The truth is you're not
going to get this in the service level
agreement though, it's just a really
good internal metric for you to track.
The other question you can ask your 3PL
is how often do they do inventory
counts?
Because especially when you get a little
bit larger, you want them to be doing
fast selling SKUs
counted fairly regularly through a cycle
count. But I would highly recommend that
no matter what business you are, at
least getting a cycle count two times a
year and having that in your service
level agreement as well. The final thing
I'll say about 3PL management is the
cheapest option is not always the best
option, because these are business
owners too. There's some of them are
very very good at what they do and
running warehouses.
And this isn't a
you know, a zero-sum game. It's not a
zero-sum relationship. You don't want to
take them to the cleaners, then to lose
money on every single order, then to
have kind of no flexibility whatsoever.
You want to build a relationship with
these people and try to give them the
benefit of the doubt. And this is where
clear communication, clear expectations
uh are actually in place. So, if you're
giving them forecasts, make sure you're
trying to hit those forecasts. Don't
give them some wild forecast that they
staff up for and then you don't actually
hit as well. So, build a really good
relationship with them, treat them with
respect, make sure they're making money
as well and it should work out well. So,
then this brings us to probably the last
side of what we're going to talk about
today, which is customer service. Now, I
highly recommend implementing a customer
service tool that can track emails if
you're not already. There's a bunch out
there. I've tested Zendesk, was too
clunky, slow, so we moved to Gorgias.
I'll leave a link in the description as
per usual.
I don't think that you 100% need to use
Gorgias. There's other options out there
and you just need to compare compare
pricing for your size of business. We
found it was most efficient and cost
effective. The truth is there's about to
be a huge disruption in that space and
whoever uses and and adapts adopts,
sorry, AI in the the fastest rate is
going to be the winner in this space.
So,
I really do recommend setting up your
customer service.
One thing that I often get asked is
international
versus local.
So, which customer service to use?
International has the benefit of them
not having similar public holidays.
Sometimes they do have public holidays,
which is great, but it's not on your
actual time zone, probably where you're
selling. And sometimes local, if
everyone is having those kind of days
off, can be extremely problematic. I
don't believe in the premise that
international using people in the
Philippines or we use some people in the
Fiji as well, is extremely cheaper,
because the efficiency of those customer
service agents can sometimes be like
double as double as good locally versus
internationally. And this is all based
on your training programs and how you
actually training these people up, as
well as how you're sorting out complex
tickets versus non-complex tickets. If
you can create a system, I believe the
best system is a blend of both at for
larger businesses. The smaller
businesses, it can be either, but for
larger businesses, you're going to want
to filter out the the easier tickets,
that they go to the the international
side of things and then the local more
nuanced things, you want people closer
to the sources of truth, closer to the
the internal team locally. So, I think
that that's one of the best ways to do
it. But this kind of brings us to how
we're measuring the effectiveness of
your customer service teams from an
operational point of view. You've got a
few metrics. First, you've got the
resolution time.
If it's taking a long time to resolve
the problem for people, one, it might be
indicative of there not being enough
visible information for people. Two, it
might be because of slow customer
service or improper systems. Three, it
might just be because you haven't set up
your macros well enough so that you can
answer customer service tickets very
very quickly. That's very similar to the
other thing, which is touch points,
which is
indicates how much how many times
actually someone needs to touch that
ticket to get the resolution for people.
This can be resolved by people just
getting more detailed replies or again,
accessibility to the the information.
Then the next thing that we have, which
will probably be correlated with
resolution time, is reviews. Now, a
great measurement of success everything
that we're talking about today
is remember, these are the this is
measurement of the outputs of our
operations. What I mean by that is
this is what the customer is
experiencing. They're experiencing
certain
resolution times around their issues,
how happy they are with the product. If
all of your operations, what we talked
about before, you don't have a tech pack
so you're getting faulty products, yeah,
it's taking too long with the the
freight side of things,
it's too expensive because you haven't
negotiated courier rates down. All of
this stuff is going to affect the
customer and affect your reviews. So,
these are great measurements of how good
are your operations. So, reviews are
great customer service metric to track
over time. The one that I wish I knew
about earlier as a business operator.
Again, we go back to our unit economic
formula for our business managing on a
daily basis, we can break that down even
more granular level for customer service
is cost per service, which is a formula
of
every single expense that you have
customer service, including the software
that you're using, the amount of agents
that you're using, the maybe you have
one agent, maybe you have five agents,
maybe you have 60 like us.
You're basically dividing every single
every single ticket that you're getting
and dividing it by the cost. Because
what you'll see, what you'll want people
to do, similar to
uh similar to the 3PL management, we
need to be forecasting our customer
service as well. Remember the diagram of
the sales coming up and down like that.
This sales forecast that we have, we're
going to want to be onboarding more
customer service agents and training
them during this period so that we have
them during peak. And this is another
reason why international customer
service is so good. You obviously need
to be very transparent. It's like, "Hey,
we need you guys during these periods."
And you can train them up. And the
local, it gets very very difficult to do
that at scale. There are some agencies
that will handle it for you locally, but
I think internationally is a little bit
better set up for for multiple reasons.
So, realistically, we want to be keeping
our cost per service relatively
consistent across the year despite our
sales coming up and down like this
because your ticket volumes are going to
increase really quickly here, but at the
same time you can increase the amount of
customer service agents that you have to
kind of match that metric. So, I think
that will do for today. It was a very
very big video. I know this stuff can be
very dry. Join the free Shopify
e-commerce course. Join the Discord if
you want to chat about any of these
these questions. If you're doing over a
million dollars in revenue, make sure
that you and any of this was kind of new
to you, you need to be joining Daily
Mentor. I promise I'll help and we'll
give you a refund if you're not happy
within the first 30 days.
No questions asked. So, yeah, I'm keen
to help. I hope
I hope you learn a lot, but yeah, don't
forget to like and subscribe as well.
Peace.